A show of two halves tonight. On one hand, Victor Frankenstein stars
Daniel Radcliffe and James McAvoy.
On the other hand, Black Mass stars Johnny Depp and Benedict Cumberbatch.
It's monsters V mobsters! Let's start the show!
This programme contains some strong language
Oh, too kind! Too kind!
Too kind! Thank you very much.
Thank you very much! Good evening and welcome! Lots of excitement tonight.
Yes, in a minute, Johnny and Benedict will be here, ladies and gentlemen.
CHEERING Yes, they will!
Calm down. Calm down, Cumberbitches
and Depp - I don't know what Depp's are. Depprobates? I don't know.
Later, I'll be joined by the stars of the new movie Victor Frankenstein -
James McAvoy and Daniel Radcliffe will be here,
ladies and gentlemen, yes, they will. CHEERING
James plays Dr Frankenstein
and Daniel is his assistant, Igor. You know Igor.
Here's a picture of Daniel
with the instructions for building the monster.
You know what it's like, they're never easy to follow, are they? No.
LAUGHTER "Finished!"
That's all to come, plus music from the fabulous Corrs!
The Corrs are back! CHEERING
But, first, he's the Oscar-nominated star who's won legions of fans
from his roles in Star Trek, The Hobbit and The Imitation Game and,
of course, his tour de force as Sherlock Holmes.
Please welcome Benedict Cumberbatch!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Hello, sir. How nice to see you.
Welcome. Thank you very much for doing this.
And one of our most brilliant and versatile actors, playing characters
from Edward Scissorhands to Willy Wonka and Captain Jack Sparrow,
currently getting the best reviews of his career in the new mobster biopic
Black Mass, it is Johnny Depp, everybody!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE Yes, it is!
Wow!
Hello, sir, lovely to see you. Sit down.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE CONTINUES
You're both very welcome. Lovely to see you both.
- Thank you very much.
- Thank you.
- I feel like we're so far apart.
Snuggle, snuggle. There you go.
That's adorable.
Ladies and gentlemen, before we do another thing,
we should congratulate you, Benedict Cumberbatch.
- The last time you were here, since then, you've become a daddy.
- I have.
- CHEERING AND WHOOPING
- Thank you very much.
And a husband as well.
- Of course, you got married.
- Yes. I did both things.
- And in the right order. Well done.
- Just.
Was it a Cumber-boy or a Cumber-girl?
It is a Cumber-boy.
LAUGHTER
- Lovely.
- A Cumberbatch boy.
- He's aiming for a batch.
- He'll go for a batch.
- I might go for a batch of Cumbers.
- Yeah.
I'll just have a batch right now.
Cheers.
Cheers, sir, cheers. Yes, cheers.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
It's like we're on a balcony looking at people in the streets. Well done.
LAUGHTER
In New Orleans.
Johnny, you've spent a lot of time in London.
Is this a kind of home from home? No.
You asked the question and then you said no.
It's sort of a no-yes, really.
I end up here a lot, working.
A lot of location stuff here.
- Well, you're very welcome.
- Thank you very much.
I was trying to get the, you know, the sir thing.
Yes! Sir Johnny Depp.
Have you met any royalty along the way?
Yeah, I did, yeah. Prince Charles and, um...
The other one.
LAUGHTER
That one.
Came to the premiere of Finding Neverland.
- Oh, OK.
- Yeah. And I, sort of, shook his hand.
He was, sort of, "Oh, rather."
I didn't understand a word he said.
And I don't think that he understood a word I said.
So it wasn't very meaningful, necessarily.
And "that one..."
seemed nice, actually.
- She did.
- I think the knighthood's in the post.
- Yeah.
The weird thing is, when you search online for people who have taken
selfies and stuff with your good self, Johnny Depp,
it seems it's not that hard to look like Johnny Depp.
- This is just...
- Wow. That's a bold claim.
No, no, wait. Here are some people out for the night.
"Oh, my God! Just met Johnny Depp and fed him a hot dog."
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
- As long as she's happy. She's happy.
- She's very, very happy.
Obviously, you're here to talk about Black Mass, which is terrific.
And the thing is, in Boston, when you were there,
it must have caused a sensation,
but then, double the chaos, because, Benedict Cumberbatch,
- wherever you go, you have very ardent fans. MUFFLED:
- I do.
- He said, "I do."
- I said I do.
Via the medium of a gin and tonic, I said I do, yes.
And somebody saw Benedict on location in Boston.
We've got a picture of you on set that day.
And so, she saw Benedict
and immediately rushed home and went on to Reddit.
She goes, "I saw BostonBatch," cos that's your name in Boston.
- It's an adaptable surname.
- Yes. "I saw Boston Batch this morning.
"Bury me in a Y-shaped coffin for I am deaded."
So, she writes, "Bitches, he is fine."
LAUGHTER
"He was wearing the blue hat, a dark blue polo shirt,
"the grey pants and white shoes.
"He's taller than I thought - I suspected he was about 5'11"
- "wannabe six-footer..."
- How dare you!
"..and ripped."
LAUGHTER
"Like, really much more muscly than I was expecting.
"Those arms, dat ass..."
LAUGHTER AND CHEERING
"..and the arm veins were in full effect. Popping.
"There was not an ounce of fat on that man, it's all muscle,
"sinewy, wholesome goodness.
"And the hat looks better in real life, too."
- What was wrong with the hat?
- The last paragraph is where
you just kind of think, "Whoa."
"I couldn't smell him.
"I really tried.
"He was so close that, had he been wearing cologne,
"I think I would've been able to tell.
"Just the lightest Cumbermusk in the Boston sunshine."
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE Are you getting it, Johnny?
Cumbermusk.
I must waft my musk in your general direction.
I gotta tell you, I can finally admit that I wrote that.
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
It's true.
Driving me wild.
My popping veins in my arms...
We must talk about Black Mass. This movie...
CHEERING
..it's kind of an instant classic.
It's had brilliant, brilliant reviews.
It's out now and it's the true story about mobster Whitey Bulger and,
Johnny, you play Whitey Bulger.
Were you aware... In this country, I'd never heard of Whitey Bulger.
- Is he famous in America? Did you know about him?
- He is.
There was a sort of fascination
with Mr Bulger.
He ran south Boston
for a number of years as this...
Well, gangster, you know.
Meanwhile, his brother was state senator
and very high up in the political ranks.
But, yeah, I just found him fascinating.
The fact that he was able to escape the Feds
and live on the run for 16 years.
When they found him,
he was in a tiny little apartment in Santa Monica.
The walls were filled with all kinds of weapons
and 800,000 in cash.
And he was living, you know, with his girlfriend, feeding cats.
Wow. Watching it, you know it's a true story, but it's sort of
- unbelievable...
- Yeah.
- ..that it was allowed to go on.
If you pitched this as a movie script...
Yeah, cos, actually, Whitey Bulger was in league with the FBI.
He was approached by the character that Joel Edgerton plays
to make a deal with the Feds
to give information about his enemies,
which were from northern Boston,
the Italians, the Cosa Nostra up there.
And they, you know, in a sense,
they gave Jimmy Bulger free rein
to do whatever he had to do.
When you see a picture of him, you don't immediately think,
"Oh, Johnny Depp, what great casting." But your transformation
- is extraordinary in the film.
- That's kind, thank you.
That is Johnny Depp. That's not him, that's Johnny Depp.
So, Benedict...
I didn't meet Johnny Depp. I met Whitey Bulger.
We met on the set and they'd been going for a while -
I think almost a month or so.
You know, it was this extraordinary thing.
I didn't meet Johnny Depp, I met Whitey Bulger.
And I only met, physically, what Johnny looks like
almost a year later in England when he was doing something here
and I was in the same studio and I put my head around the corner
and went, "Hello." It set our friendship back about six notches.
I was at the embarrassed, "Oh, my God, I'm meeting Johnny Depp," stage
rather than somebody who'd already just played his brother.
So, for you, it's a challenging thing to play a person from Boston,
but you're playing someone who's
a well-known, well-liked local figure.
- That's a lot of pressure.
- It is a bit, it is a bit.
On the first day, I was leading this big St Patrick's Day parade,
which he did as President of the State Senate
and there he is doing it.
And the guy behind me was leading a pipe band.
It was the most amazing day of filming, actually.
It was just this incredible array of people doing very authentic work
from that period in recreating this parade.
And this guy doing the pipes behind me said, "Who are you playing?"
I went, "Billy Bulger." "You look nothing like him."
I'll get back on the plane, then.
In all honesty, I had a couple of prosthetics put on my cheeks to try
and get me a little bit rounder face, cos of my weird long face.
And I was, actually - God bless that woman/Johnny Depp for noticing that
I was quite muscly at the time, because I'd been working out a lot,
cos I'm taller than him,
- to try and look broader so I could try and play squatter.
- Oh!
LAUGHTER
That came with a lot of work. I didn't wake up looking like that.
- Does that not make you feel better, though?
- Ohh...
Crushed her again.
THEY LAUGH
So, yeah, it was a lot of fun.
It's unbelievable. You're both great in it.
This is a clip from the movie and this is the two of you
- spending some quality family time.
- Mm.
Gin.
Come on. Not again.
You're not paying attention.
Can't you see I'm after hearts and you just keep feeding me hearts.
I'm getting creamed over here.
Didn't you learn nothing in prison?
All those hours and no-one taught you how to play gin.
Well, they didn't teach me how to cheat against my mom.
Look, here's my cards, count 'em.
Hey, Ma, did you hear old Mother Burke died over on Baker Street?
- No-one found her for a couple of weeks.
- That's right.
When they broke down the door,
the cats had devoured the best part of her.
That's beautiful, Ma. Who's hungry?
I'm out. I got creamed. I'm going to take a nap. Thanks for cheating, Ma.
See you later.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Watching the movie, it happens so fast, you forget it's Johnny Depp.
- It's weird.
- I hope so. That's the...
That's the goal, you know.
And, you know, obviously you go through creating characters,
but to come up with something as quirky as Captain Jack...
WHOOPING Yes.
APPLAUSE
But then, to have him be so loved...
and we've seen those pictures of you when you visit hospitals and schools
and that must be an amazing gift to be able to give those people.
I mean, for me, it's the gift. They're giving me the gift,
because to go into a place...
where, you know, I mean...
I've spent time in Great Ormond Street,
where I was the parent,
when my daughter was ill, and it was...
I mean, I've known darkness in my life,
but that was the darkest period ever.
It was when I was doing Sweeney and...
I'd always done these visits, but after that, the visits became
more and more important,
because the kids, bless them,
they're so strong, they're so courageous...
but the parents are the ones who are slowly dying,
and to be able to bring a smile or a giggle to these people...
it means everything in the world to me, you know. Far more than...
APPLAUSE
And, obviously, another great creation,
Benedict's Sherlock Holmes, ladies and gentlemen.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
On Mastermind there. 1900s.
I have to ask...I know you can't tell me anything,
- so Christmas, it's back.
- Yes.
- Is it just one episode at Christmas?
- You can tell me that.
- Yes.
Sorry, that was bad. Yes, it's just a one-off Christmas special.
- Is that the one where...?
- I rang up the other day and, literally, like,
"No, I can't talk about that, can't talk about that, can't really
"talk about that. Whatever can I talk about on this sofa?"
No, it's great, it's fantastic and I haven't seen it,
so I can't even say that, really.
But is this the one? Cos we've seen some stills -
- this is the one set in...
- Old Victorian London, yeah,
the original Conan Doyle setting.
- Fog and all.
- And it's one episode?
You'll just have to wait and see.
All right, I did ask!
I can't take it, please!
I beg you!
Now, along with great fame comes great fandom
and along with great fandom come weirdos.
LAUGHTER
We have discussed this on the show before -
I don't know, are you aware of this, Johnny Depp?
That when Benedict became famous,
one of the first things that happened was his fans - this is so random -
his fans decided that he looked very like an otter. Are you aware of this?
I'm sorry?
LAUGHTER
You would think, We've shown these before, these are classics.
- An otter?
- Otter, you know, a creature.
- Him, an otter?
- Yeah.
- He looks like an otter.
- I can only imagine what mine would be!
We may find out. Here is a classic otter.
And you think...it does look...
LAUGHTER
Here is a more expressive otter.
And, see?
LAUGHTER
And this next one you would think, "How can he look like this?"
And here you go, there he is.
- Now...
- May I say one thing?
- Yes.
Someone has a lot of time on their hands.
You know what's annoying, though? They don't have enough time
on their hands, because there aren't really any more out there.
- So, would you be up for matching some pictures of otters?
- Yeah.
I'll return the favour, yes.
AMERICAN ACCENTS: And then, it'll go viral and it'll be great.
- It'll be super.
- It'll be amazing.
- People will like viral pictures
of me and an otter and will go and see a film about a violent gangster,
- yay!
- You know how this works!
I'm sort of scared of otters.
You won't be after... Well, actually, this first otter,
I'm afraid, it's the dark side of the otter kingdom.
This is angry otter.
LAUGHTER
It makes you love otters. Can you do that? Can you try it?
It's good!
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE Excellent.
- That's really good.
- Was it all right?
OK, this next one is also a slightly aggressive otter.
It's a bit fisty, it's a bit like, "Why I outta...!"
Other way.
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
These are good, these are good.
They start to get more challenging. They start to get more challenging.
What the hell? Can you attempt that?
Yeah. OK...
- Tongue that way.
- I go to that one and it's the other way!
This is really weird.
Very good!
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
Now, this is an opportunity for...
Is that casting for my next role as an otter?
No, no, you're in it. You're the star.
This is an opportunity for myself and Johnny
to channel our inner otter. This is a nice three shot.
LAUGHTER
- If you lean in, I'll lean in.
- Oh, to me?
- Yes, you're in the middle.
- Wait, wait, what's the face on the other...?
- OK, OK.
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
Adorable. Adorable.
So then, we found this picture.
We found this picture of an otter, look at this. Look at this.
Let's have a close-up of the face. You've never seen a happier creature
on planet Earth. Look how happy this otter is with his new teddy bear.
LAUGHTER
The teddy bear doesn't look very happy.
No, the teddy bear's quite depressed.
"I've been given to a mammal."
I sent out the command, I picked up my phone and I went,
"We'll need a big teddy bear."
However, the word "big" is relative.
They've gone with a really enormous teddy bear.
- So, it's over there.
- Ah!
- LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
- Wow!
Isn't that amazing?
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
That is genius.
- I've always wanted to do something...
- Oh, oh, oh, oh.
It's just, there's something... I don't know, there's something
about it that makes me want to kind of do this.
Oh!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
- Don't kick the bear!
- Think I'm a cute otter?
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
Your otter business is over.
That's versatility.
DROWNED OUT BY APPLAUSE
Well done to all the otters.
We're out of time, so all that remains to do is remind everybody
that Black Mass is out now.
It's a stunning, stunning film. You're both so good in it.
Please, go and see it. Huge thank you to Mr Benedict Cumberbatch
and Johnny Depp, everybody.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Right. Right.
My next guests tonight are two
of our finest young actors.
One came to our attention in brilliant films
like the Last King Of Scotland and Atonement,
and then found global acclaim
as the young Professor Xavier in the X-Men series.
The other has made the leap from most successful child actor of all time
to star in movies like the Woman In Black and Kill Your Darlings.
They're now starring together in Victor Frankenstein. Here's a taste.
Victor.
Igor.
- I'm so glad you've come!
- Victor, Finnegan tried to have me killed.
I believe he intends to kill you when you've outlived your usefulness
and given him what he wants.
Now, we could still get out of this, but you must stop this experiment.
- Father has sent you.
- Don't be ridiculous!
He'll stop at nothing and you don't know what he's capable of.
- I don't care.
- What?
Finnegan's motives mean nothing to me.
I will turn the tide of human existence here tonight
and this world, which has spurned me, will forever remember my name.
No, no, if you do what he asks no-one will remember
Frankenstein the man, only the monster.
Ooh, angry face!
Please welcome James McAvoy and Daniel Radcliffe.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
INDISTINCT GREETINGS
- Daniel's changed!
- I know!
- Yes.
- What happened to you? Head lice, what happened?
- Yes. Exactly.
I've just finished filming a film called Imperium,
which is about an FBI agent that goes undercover with a bunch of
sort of Nazi skinheads. Well, not sort of Nazi skinheads,
- ACTUAL Nazi skinheads.
- It's a musical.
But you're only pretending.
Yes, absolutely. This is in no way reflects my political views.
- James, we have seen you with shaved head.
- Oh, yeah.
- Was this for the new X-Men?
- Yes, where I finally go bald.
- So we finally find out...
- That's what it's called. X-Men - Goes Bald.
Triple X. You know.
Is there a good reason why he goes bald or is it really dull?
He ends up doing something so horrible and so physically painful
he, literally, half pulls his hair out, half it falls out.
- Maybe...or maybe not.
- Were you supposed to tell us that?
Yeah, I know. I've just shit myself,
because Fox Studios - who own me -
might be angry with me for saying that.
- There is now a red dot on your forehead.
- It might be a prank.
Him and Magneto are just having a couple of drinks.
He passes out and wakes up with his eyebrows shaved off
and his hair and he's got no pubes.
LAUGHTER
Toothpaste on his nipples. You know. We've all done it.
You're here to talk about Victor Frankenstein,
- which opens next Thursday, the 3rd December.
- Yes.
Even the movie, cos you start the movie in your voiceover as Igor
and you're saying, "This is a story you know,"
- but it is a totally new kind of retelling of this story.
- It is.
You know, Frankenstein, I haven't read the book
and I've seen very few of the films other than Young Frankenstein.
He hasn't read the script, either!
It's very good. It's very good.
Yeah, Igor, my character, is not in the book.
That became a part of the legend of Frankenstein in pop culture,
and so if anyone was thinking, when they saw that clip,
"He has no hunchback," don't worry,
there is serious, very severe hunchback going on.
Lovers of hunchback acting will not be disappointed.
This is the movie for you.
"Come for the hunchback, stay for the monster."
It is too late to change the posters?
And I like sort of doing, you know, contorting myself
and doing weird stuff physically - that sounds wrong!
But I do and so, yeah, that was a lot of fun.
Unfortunately, I only have to do it
- for the first 20 pages of the script.
- Yes, because who knew
the good doctor "cures" the hunchback.
Lumbago, bunions, cold and flu, hunchback - I'm on it, mate.
It turns out it's disgusting but quite simple.
Yeah, you suck it out.
- My favourite scene in the film.
- You don't swallow. You don't swallow.
- You must swallow a bit.
- Only to make him feel nice.
Make him feel like I care.
What a good doctor!
"I must go back to him."
Yeah, we had this thing where it was meant to be syringed out.
You stick a big, old medical syringe in and pull it out.
And the minute I read it, I thought I would love to sort of do that,
but also, I had this image of siphoning...when you siphon...
You know when you siphon petrol out of somebody's car?
Have you stolen diesel?
Yes. Not because I was going to use it, just for a laugh.
And I thought we should suck it
and get the pus flowing, as it were.
AUDIENCE GROANS
Can I say, this description is really not as disgusting as it is.
- It's really great.
- And then, you're going to get a bit of blowback
in your mouth.
Then, you get it out and you start it flowing and that drains the sack,
as it were.
But there was a great moment - this was not in the script -
James was coming up with it on set
and we were working out the logistics of it and were all like,
"This is great!" And me, James and Paul were getting excited,
like three kids, about this hilarious, gross,
brilliant idea we'd had. And then, I just remember walking off the set
and seeing a couple of producers clearly just thinking,
"What?! We need to separate them!"
This was our first day together on set, by the way.
This is James' first day on set. It was great.
So, now, here's a thing. We know, Daniel Radcliffe, you have
a reputation for being lovely to fans, very sweet,
you give your time freely to them, but I read with interest
that you are starting to toughen up now,
- you're being a bit more discerning with your fans.
- Erm...
LAUGHTER
What do you mean?
Well, you were being generally nice, but you were with a friend
- and she kind of went...
- Oh, yes, right!
Well, yeah. Well, cos I...
I think when you start acting at a young age,
people expect you to be a total dick all the time, and that is
the expectation you always find yourself coming up against.
And so, I think, all my life, I've worked hard to not be that
and to be as far away from that as possible.
But that has sometimes meant that you can be really rude to me
and I'll just be like, "Yeah, fine."
I won't notice you've been rude.
Sometimes, people will come up...
99% of the time, when people come up to you and ask you for something
on the street, they are really very nice and then just occasionally...
Somebody said, "Can I get a picture with you?"
I just, you know, saying words, not meaning anything by it,
I just said, "Oh, yeah, of course, if you want to." And she just went,
"Well, I wouldn't have asked if I didn't want to."
I was like, "No, of course, you wouldn't. How silly of me."
Then she left. My girlfriend was with me and she was like,
"That girl was a dick to you."
So she's given me a little bit of sense of...
like, you can judge that. Not that I'm a dick back now or anything.
But, apparently, Rupert Grint's even worse than you.
Rupert - I don't know the details of this at all - but Rupert ended up
at somebody's house one night,
just from continuing to say yes to things.
"Hey, do you want to do that? Do you want to do that?" "Yeah, yeah."
- We've all been there, Daniel.
- LAUGHTER
I feel bad saying this cos I feel like somebody is going to take
advantage of that and he's going to be like the new
Manchurian candidate or something.
Sometimes people come up to you and they don't mean to be rude,
- but they can be quite rude, can't they, James?
- Oh, yeah.
At the premiere of Suffragette - my wife had just been in a film -
and I thought, if anybody calls out my name, I'll sign autographs,
and as it happened, a few people shouted and I did that.
And so this woman was screaming, screaming, screaming,
"James! James! James! Sign my thing, sign my thing, sign my thing!"
And I came over and she went, "Oh, thank you.
"I'm a really big fan of SOME of your work."
LAUGHTER
"Oh, er, I think, yeah. Thank you. I'll sign SOME of your posters."
That was weird. People are trying to be nice.
Sometimes, as well, there's a thing people do, and it is particularly
young men with me, want to do a thing where they want me to know
that they don't give a shit about me before they ask for something.
So they'll be like, "Didn't really like the Harry Potter movies,
"but can you sign this?"
I'm like, "Don't do that! Say a nice thing." It's so easy.
I had one happen really recently at a fancy dress party where, um...
And this is weird, right?
Do you know that thing where people make a list of famous people
that they're allowed to have sex with if they meet them?
- Oh, the free pass.
- The free pass. She called it an allowance.
LAUGHTER
I was like, "What, like pocket money?
"How are you going to spend me?"
So...I met her and her fella
and then, she came up and said afterwards, she went,
"So, you're my allowance."
I was like, "I beg your... Excuse me?"
She went, "You know, he's cool with it and you're my thing."
I was like, "Er..."
He's not cool with it, by the way.
By the way, that's a whole other story.
I was really taken aback by it and I was like,
"I'm married but thank you very much, it's very nice of you."
Then she said this thing, it was meant as a compliment and she was
trying to get me to do stuff, but it was still really backhanded.
And she went, "Cos, you know,
"a lot of girls would be after somebody like Channing Tatum."
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
I was like, "Do you know what? You're no gettin' it."
LAUGHTER
Achievable goals.
The thing is, if people want a picture of Daniel and you think,
"I'm never going to meet Daniel Radcliffe," don't worry.
Because have you seen - you like the internet -
have you seen this thing on Reddit?
I've been made aware of this, I think. Is this time travelling me?
Yeah, the Daniel Radcliffe time traveller.
- People post old photographs and...
- I look like everyone...
- You really do.
So people post old photographs and you have to scan them very carefully
to see if you can manage to spot who in the photograph
looks like Daniel Radcliffe.
So, can you spot Daniel Radcliffe time traveller in this picture?
LAUGHTER
Got him!
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
The next one is easier because there are three people.
Can you see which of the three people is Daniel Radcliffe time traveller?
LAUGHTER
- That is you!
- Pictures of me, particularly when I was younger,
that is very, very, very close to how I was.
And if Daniel Radcliffe ever went on Who Do You Think You Are?
At some point, surely this photograph will come up.
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
Right, it's music time.
This band have sold over 40 million records,
been nominated for two Grammys and now, after ten years
out of the spotlight, they're back with their sixth studio album.
Performing their current single, Bring On The Night,
please welcome the Corrs!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
# I read the book you read
# Tasted the words you said
# Our story is darkening with time
# One fading afternoon
# And I'll miss you for ever
# Let's hope we've always summer
# Yeah, bring on the night, I don't care
# Bring on the night, I don't care
# Turn on the dark I'm not scared
# Turn on the dark, I'm not scared
# Wherever it is
# You left me behind
# I'll follow you down
# The path of my broken heart
# Flowers on Edith Grove
# Wilt like a love note
# Every day I'm passing by
# I say a little prayer
# And I'll miss you forever
# Let's hope we've always summer
# Yeah, bring on the night I don't care
# Bring on the night, I don't care
# Turn on the dark, I'm not scared
# Turn on the dark I'm not scared
# Spirit run to a flame
# Ask that I'll see you again
# Yeah, bring on the night I don't care
# Bring on the night, I don't care
# Turn on the dark, I'm not scared
# Turn on the dark I'm not scared
# Wherever it is
# You left me behind
# I'll follow you down
# The path of my broken
# Heart
# Ohhh
# And I'll miss you for ever
# Let's hope we've always summer
# Yeah, bring on the night, I don't care
# Bring on the night, I don't care
# Turn on the dark, I'm not scared
# Turn on the dark I'm not scared
# Spirit run to a flame
# Ask that I'll see you again
# Yeah, bring on the night I don't care
# Bring on the night, I don't care
# Turn on the dark, I'm not scared
# Turn on the dark I'm not scared
# Wherever it is
# You left me behind
# I'll follow you down
# The path of my broken heart. #
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
The Corrs, ladies and gentlemen!
Come and join us.
Come on. The Corrs, everybody!
Hello. Welcome back. Welcome back. Welcome back.
INDISTINCT GREETINGS
The gang's all here.
OK, sit down, sit down, sit down.
All right, just sit down!
Just sit down!
So, welcome back, the Corrs.
That is a track from the album White Light,
which, as chance would have it,
is out today. There you go.
APPLAUSE
Got a round of applause!
Are you back because it's ten years?
It wasn't really a plan of ten years or anything like that,
it was kind of Caroline suggested it...last September.
Yeah, I just thought maybe it would be nice thing for us to perform
and write together again, so we finally got it together.
And you are touring, so when does that start?
- We start on the 19th. The 19th of January...
- We need the month.
..in Birmingham.
"The 19th."
We're doing London and Dublin and Belfast. Should be great,
we're looking forward to it as well, then, we branch out into Europe
- after that.
- Ladies and gentlemen, you look at this couch and you would
be right when you thought, "There are award-winners on that couch," cos,
Andrea, you're the Most Beautiful Woman in the World?
- A lot of years ago!
- Stop that!
Untouched by time.
Where did you win the Most Beautiful Woman in the World title?
I don't actually know which poll it was.
Oh, look at her pretending not to remember.
For the last ten years, you've been getting it out going, "Look at that."
Every day, dusting it.
James, you're not the most...
Well... Sorry, I nearly said...
- Whoa, whoa, whoa.
- You are ONE of the most Beautiful Men in the World.
Not as beautiful as Channing fucking Tatum.
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
No. No, you are not.
- I'm about to play his boss, by the way, so, you know...
- Ooh-ho!
- What's that in?
- He's going to be Gambit and I'm Professor X,
so I can tell him to go and like, I don't know, get fat.
- "Eat this." In improv, just bringing doughnuts.
- Steady now.
No, food. But, ladies and gentlemen,
most exciting of all, we have a current - a CURRENT -
award winner. Yes, actual 2015's holder of, Daniel Radcliffe?
Rear of the Year.
CHEERING AND WHISTLING
- I carry it with me everywhere I go.
- Oh, you have it!
- Absolutely!
Yeah, I brought it, obviously.
Where did you get it from?
- Girls, ladies, check it out.
- Very nice.
It's too bright to look at.
It's like looking at the sun.
I don't mean this to come across as slightly ungrateful, but do you not
think, like, the Rear of the Year award should look like an arse?
- Like, I don't know...
- Like yours, it should be moulded perfectly.
Or like a hand doing that.
LAUGHTER
More like this.
Oh, that's good, I like that.
- But, still, I was chuffed.
- Was it a glittering occasion?
No, it was just me in my room, voting again and again.
LAUGHTER
Did you go somewhere to pick it up?
No, I think they sent it to my agent.
- In a padded envelope?
- Parcelforce.
- Well done.
- "Can you sign for this?"
2016, James, it could be yours.
I'm down the gym, I'm doing my squats.
LAUGHTER
Listen, Corrs, thank you very much for coming back. We missed you,
we're glad you're back.
Good luck with the album, good luck with the tour. The Corrs, everybody.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Before we go, you know what is going to happen now.
Yes, this week's visit to the Big Red Chair. Who's there?
- Hello.
- You're on, yeah. Hi, how are you?
- Petrified.
Oh, don't be scared. What is your name?
- Sylvia.
- lovely. And what do you do, Sylvia?
- Sorry?!
LAUGHTER
- What do you do?
- Ah, what do I do? I stay at home with my dog.
- OK.
LAUGHTER
- Who is looking after the dog tonight?
- Oh, God, my husband.
LAUGHTER
She can stay in the chair, as far as I'm concerned.
- Where are you from originally?
- I am Peruvian.
- Peruvian.
- Yes.
- I don't believe we've had a Peruvian on the Red Chair before.
- Yeah.
So... Yeah, OK.
I'm not an acting coach or anything, I cannot read these expressions.
Her excitement...her face seems so upset.
- I am the first Peruvian to do this ridiculous thing.
- OK.
Sylvia, focus.
- You are representing Peru.
- OK.
- Off you go with your story.
OK, so here we are at Heathrow with my husband and he said to me,
"Go and see which belt number our luggage is coming out."
"OK," I said. "Don't move, stay here."
Off I went, a few steps, came back and said, "Number this."
And then, I felt quite chilly.
Put my arm around him and then, I felt very chilly.
I started putting my hand inside his trouser pocket
when, suddenly, I felt everybody looking at me. Oh, my God.
I lean over, looked to the right and saw these two huge eyes.
They were the wife's eyes and I was embracing the wrong husband!
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
What did you want to do? You wanted that to happen.
Well done, the Big Red Chair. If you would like to join us on the show
and have a go in that red chair,
you can. Contact us via the website at this very address -
That's it. Just a big thank you to my guests tonight - Johnny Depp
and Benedict Cumberbatch.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE The Corrs.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE Daniel Radcliffe.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE And James McAvoy.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Join me next week with comedian Kevin Bridges,
director Ron Howard, Hollywood hunk Chris Hemsworth
and the comedy legend that is Lily Tomlin.
I will see you then. Goodnight, everybody, bye-bye!